A Guide to the Legislative Petitions of the General Assembly, 1776-1865
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Legislative Petitions of the General Assembly, 1776-1865
The Library of Virginia
36121
273 cubic feet
Virginia General Assembly
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Acquisition information unknown.
Alternative Form Available
Available on microfilm.
Historical Information
The legislative branch of government in Virginia is the oldest of its kind in the Western Hemisphere, tracing its lineage to the first meeting of the Grand Assembly of governor, councilors, and burgesses at Jamestown on July 30, 1619. Beginning with the session convened on March 2, 1643, an assembly was constituted with a House of Burgesses modeled after the House of Commons in Parliament, with the governor's Council serving as the upper house. Upon adoption of the first state constitution in 1776, the General Assembly was restructured to consist of the House of Delegates and the Senate. The General Assembly is composed of 40 Senators, elected every four years and 100 delegates, elected every two years, who formulate and enact laws in the Commonwealth. Major activities of the state legislature include representing citizens in the formulation of public policy, enacting statutory laws providing a statutory and financial basis for all government actions, electing judicial officers, and confirming executive appointments of the governor.
In the General Assembly, members of the House of Delegates and the Senate vote on legislation entered during the legislative sessions. Legislative bills can originate in either the House or the Senate, with both chambers having the ability to establish study committees. Each house serves as a check on the other to ensure a thorough debate on the merits of each bill. Currently the General Assembly holds annual sessions, alternately of thirty or sixty days' duration.
Scope and Content
The Legislative Petitions of the General Assembly are housed in 370 boxes and are arranged in five series. Series have been designated for Counties, Cities, Kentucky Counties, Miscellaneous (Chronological), and Miscellaneous (Alphabetical). The Counties & Cities are arranged in alphabetical order by locality, then chronological. The Kentucky petitions are arranged in chronological order. There are two series for miscellaneous petitions, one arranged in chronological order - Miscellaneous (Chronological), and one arranged in alphabetical order - Miscellaneous (Alphabetical). Petitions to the General Assembly were the primary catalyst for legislation in the Commonwealth from 1776 until 1865. Public improvements, military claims, divorce, manumission of slaves, division of counties, incorporation of towns, religious freedom, and taxation were just some of the concerns expressed in these petitions. The petitions often contain hundreds of signatures and are a useful tool in genealogical research. Frequently, the petitions contain supplementary support documents useful in research including maps, wills, naturalizations, deeds, resolutions, affidavits, judgments, and other items.
A database, accessible through the website of The Library of Virginia ( http://www.virginiamemory.com/collections/petitions ), was created to calendar the Legislative Petitions. The database lists the name of the petitioner, locality, date of presentation, description, reel number, box number, and folder number. In addition, each petition has been assigned one or more topics for indexing purposes. The petitions have been assigned with the following topics: Agriculture/Livestock/Farming; Appropriations/Salary Increases; Banks & Banking; Bridges; Canals; Charters/Incorporations; Churches/Religious Issues; Citizenship/Naturalizations; Commerce; Constitutional Conventions; Courts/Judicial System; Division of County/New County; Divorce; Elections; Ferries/Packets; Fishing/Oyster Industry; Free Negroes; Indians; Land/Real Estate; Manufacturers/Manufacturing Companies; Militia/Public Guard; Mining/Mining Companies; Miscellaneous; Name Changes; Navigation/Navigation Companies; Organizations; Paper Money; Pardons/Release from Fines, Judgments, etc; Private Relief/Compensation; Prohibition/Temperance; Railroads/Railroad Companies; Revenue/Taxation; Roads/Turnpike Companies; Schools/Universities; Slaves/Slavery; Tobacco Inspection/Industry; Towns; War Claims/Pensions; and Wills/Administrations.
Agriculture/Livestock/Farming - There are 384 petitions in the database related to agriculture, livestock, or farming. These petitions are from farmers, agricultural societies, and others. The petitions relate to declaring waterways as lawful fences, the incorporation of agricultural societies, bounties for wolf & fox scalps for the protection of livestock, taxes on dogs, legislation respecting enclosures, the driving of livestock, the production of silk, the prohibition of the distillation of grain during the Civil War, and prohibitions against hogs & other livestock from running at large in towns.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: Edmund Ruffin, Chairman of the Committee of the State Agricultural Club, asking for the enactment of some proper measures in aid of agricultural instruction & improvement (Nelson Co. - 1851/02/12); Edmund Ruffin asking for a law requiring the Commissioners of the Revenue of the counties to ascertain the quantities of all lands marled or limed (Hanover Co. - 1852/02/12); the Virginia State Agricultural Society asking for an act of incorporation (Richmond City - 1850/03/04); and Committee of the Farmer's Assembly asking for the establishment of a professorship of agriculture upon a donation of Philip St. John Cocke at the University of Virginia (Albemarle Co. - 1957/12/21).
Appropriations/Salary Increases - There are 888 petitions in the database related to requests for appropriations by the Legislature and salary increases. There are petitions from commissioners of revenue, colonization societies, inspectors of tobacco, clerks, sheriffs, trustees of colleges, and other citizens. The petitions relate to appropriations for internal improvements, colleges & academies, and salary increases for tobacco inspectors, clerks, and other state employees.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: James Warrell asking for an appropriation for the repair of the roof of his museum erected on Capitol Square (Richmond City - 1821/12/19); William Tatham asking for an appropriation to complete his map of the Southern Division of the United States (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1791/10/31); Trustees of the Deaf & Dumb Asylum asking for an appropriation (Augusta Co. - 1833/12/28); Samuel P. Parsons, Superintendent of the Penitentiary, asking for a salary increase (Richmond City - 1818/01/02 & 1818/12/23); Blair Bolling, Commandant of the Public Guard, asking for compensation for his services as Superintendent of Public Buildings (Richmond City - 1831/02/18); Cadets of the Virginia Military Institute asking for an appropriation to reconstruct & enlarge their barracks (Rockbridge Co. - 1849/01/03); Cavalry & Volunteer Corps asking for an appropriation to convey the remains of Light Horse Harry Lee from Georgia to Virginia (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1861/01/15); Citizens of Albemarle County asking for an appropriation to erect a marble statue in honor of Thomas Jefferson at the University of Virginia (1850/12/04); Richard Oglesby Davidson asking for an appropriation to aid his enterprise in constructing a machine to be employed in the navigation of the air (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1841/02/10); Directors of Public Buildings asking for additional funds for the completion of the Capitol (Richmond City - 1786/12/06); Andrew Dunscomb asking for additional allowance as commissioner for adjusting the accounts of the Commonwealth against the United States (Richmond City - 1790/11/16); Inhabitants of Richmond asking for aid in the establishment of a library and depository of the arts & sciences on Capitol Square (1817/12/20); and the Mayor, Recorder, Aldermen, & Common Council of Williamsburg asking for an appropriation for rebuilding the former Capitol or granting the lot on which it stands (1832/12/10).
Banks & Banking - There are 619 records in the database related to banks & banking. Included are petitions from presidents & boards of directors of banks, citizens, merchants, stockholders, and others. These petitions relate to the incorporation of banks, the renewal or extension of banks charters, the establishment of branches of the Bank of Virginia, Exchange Bank of Virginia, North Western Bank of Virginia, etc., permissions to issue notes of less denomination, and increases in the capital of banks.
Bridges - These are 534 records in the database related to bridges. These petitions originate from citizens, bridge companies, and turnpike companies concerning the construction & repair of bridges, increases in tolls, lotteries, and protests against the construction of bridges. Among the bridge companies are the Covington Bridge Company, Wheeling & Belmont Bridge Company, Morgantown Bridge Company, Norfolk Draw Bridge Company, and Potomac Bridge Company.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: William Edloe & Goodrich Durfey asking for permission to erect a bridge across the creek separating Jamestown Island from the mainland (James City Co. - 1832/01/24 & Williamsburg - 1833/01/12); Justices of the Peace, Mayor, Aldermen, & Commonalty of Richmond requesting a sum of money for erecting a stone bridge across Shockoe Creek (Henrico County - 1792/10/03); Abigail Mayo regarding tolls on Mayo's Bridge (Richmond City - 1830's); John Mayo asking for permission to build a bridge across the James River between Richmond & Manchester (Richmond City - 1784/11/25); citizens of Henrico & Richmond against the petitions of Edward W. Trent & others for leave to erect a toll bridge across the James River (Henrico Co. - 1813/12/07 & Richmond City - 1815/12/18 & 26); and W. J. Willey & others of Monongalia County asking for an increase in the capital stock of the Morgantown Bridge Company including a plan of the Morgantown Wire Suspension Bridge (1850/12/12).
Canals - There are 223 petitions related to canals. The petitions are from citizens, the Covington Convention, the Chesapeake & Ohio Canal Convention, and various canal companies including the James River & Kanawha Canal Company, the Chesapeake & Ohio Canal Company, the Dismal Swamp Canal Company, the Potomac Company, the Rappahannock Company, & the Alexandria Canal Company. These petitions relate to subscriptions to capital stock, amendments to charters, appropriations, incorporations, lotteries, tolls, and extensions.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: Covington Convention asking for the extension of the James River Canal to Covington (various counties - 1847/01/05) and President & Directors of the Potomac Company asking that acts may pass by the Assemblies of Virginia & Maryland for a canal at each or either of the Great Falls (signed by George Washington) (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1785/12/09 & 1786/11/09).
Charters/Incorporations - There are 2,493 records in the database related to charters & incorporations. Included are petitions from organizations, academies & colleges, railroad companies, cities, churches, mining companies, manufactories, temperance societies, fraternal organizations, turnpike companies, library companies, fire companies, trade associations, merchants, banks, navigation companies, town officials, trustees, and others. These petitions relate to acts of incorporations, alterations & extensions to charters, and repeals of acts of incorporations.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: Robert Briggs & others asking for the incorporation of the Medical College of Virginia (Richmond City - 1835/12/23 & 1836/12/31); petitions for & against the incorporations of the Protestant Episcopal Church (various localities - 1786); Citizens of Lynchburg asking for an act incorporating the town (1804/12/08); Citizens of Hampton asking for a law incorporating the town (Elizabeth City Co. - 1849/01/06); Citizens of Harpers Ferry and North & South Bolivar asking for the incorporation of the town of Harpers Ferry (Jefferson Co. - 1850/12/09); petitions from lodges of the Independent Order of Odd Fellows & divisions of the Sons of Temperance (various localities & dates); devisees of Gen. George Washington asking that the Dismal Swamp Company choose a president & managers and that they be incorporated (Miscellaneous (Alphabetical) - Box 303, Folder 52); Free & Accepted Masons lodges (various localities & dates); Hollywood Cemetery Company asking for an act of incorporation (Richmond City - 1849/12/27); Thomas Hudgins & others asking for the incorporation of Richmond College (Richmond City - 1840/01/02); Inhabitants of Alexandria asking for the incorporation of the town (1778/12/03); Inhabitants of Richmond asking for the incorporation of the town (Richmond City - 1782/05/28 (original missing) & 1793/11/04); Inhabitants of Lexington & Fayette Co., Kentucky, asking for the incorporation of the town of Lexington (Kentucky Counties - 1787/11/06); Inhabitants of Yorktown asking for an act incorporating the town (York Co. - 1780/05/10); and Trustees of the Deaf & Dumb Asylum asking for an act of incorporation (Augusta Co. - 1833/12/28).
Churches/Religious Issues - There are 736 records in the database relating to churches and various religious issues. Petitions can be found from Baptist Associations, churchwardens, vestry, clergy, dissenters, churches, overseers of the poor, Quakers, trustees, and other citizens. These petitions relate to the dissolution of vestries, glebe lands, the incorporation of the Protestant Episcopal Church, exemptions from militia duty, lotteries, provisions for teachers of the Protestant Episcopal Church, the disestablishment of the Church of England, parish divisions, the sale of goods & liquor close to religious assemblies & places of worship, and authority to hold bequests for religious, benevolent, & literary societies.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: Peter Deforest asking for compensation for his service as minister of the gospel in the Penitentiary (Richmond City - 1850/03/18); Dissenters asking for the disestablishment of the Church of England (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1776/10/16); Dover Baptist Association asking for a law to protect their rights to worship freely (Northumberland Co. - 1820/12/08); Free persons of color in Richmond, as well as slaves, asking for authority to perform the ceremony of the burial of the dead (1834/12/17); Jacob A. Levy & Jacob Ezekiel asking for the remission of fines imposed on them as Jews for violating the Sabbath (Richmond City - 1846/02/20 & 1848/03/08); Religious society of Friends asking for the interference of the Legislature for remedying abuses in the traffic of slaves from Virginia to other states (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1802/12/17); and Trustees of the Theological Seminary of Virginia asking to be incorporated (Prince Edward Co. - 1815/12/07).
Citizenship/Naturalizations - There are 37 records in the database concerning citizenship & naturalizations. These petitions relate to citizens' requests for citizenship, permissions for foreign-born inhabitants to hold real estate, and restoration of rights of citizenship. Some petitions include certificates of naturalization, oaths of allegiance, & certificates of declaration.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: Freeholders of Hanover & Henrico protesting against the bill to exclude particular classes of British subjects from the rights of citizenship within the Commonwealth (Hanover Co. - 1783/06/06 & Henrico Co. - 1783/06/01) and Citizens of Loudoun County asking for an act to prohibit hawkers & peddlers in co-partnership from trading under the same license and to raise the license of those not naturalized or to prohibit them from trading at all (1842/01/03).
Commerce - There are 230 records in the database related to commerce. The petitions originate from citizens, merchants, traders, and others. The petitions relate to the revision of the revenue & license laws, license taxes, merchants' licenses, prohibitions against trading at meetings for religious worship, illegal dealings with slaves, vending of ardent spirits, restriction of foreign vessels to certain ports, and embargoes.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: Citizens of Cumberland County asking for enactments in aid & defense of the trade, industry, & proprietary & political rights of the people of the Commonwealth involved in the institution of slavery in the states where the institution now exists (1860/01/05); Macon Convention regarding free trade, weights & measures, taxation, pilot laws, etc., within the Confederate States (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1861/10/14); D. H. London, President of the Southern Rights Association of Virginia, asking for excise laws discriminating in favor of articles grown, manufactured, or imported from Virginia (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1851/01/31); and Merchants, Traders, & other inhabitants of Fredericksburg asking for the removal of restrictions to trade between the United States & British West Indies (1784/11/04).
Constitutional Conventions - There are 212 records in the database regarding the elections for conventions to alter & amend the state constitution. In addition, there are protests against the Staunton Convention calling for a convention to expand suffrage and consider the present system of apportionment. Noteworthy are the following petitions: Inhabitants of the Kentucky River asking for the admission of John Gabriel Jones & George Rogers Clark as duly elected delegates to the May 1776 Convention (Fincastle Co. - 1776/10/08) and Staunton Convention asking for the election of a convention to alter & amend the defects of the constitution (Augusta Co. - 1816/11/18).
Courts/Judicial System - These are 1,776 records in the database related to courts and judicial system in Virginia. Included are petitions from citizens, attorneys, county & corporation courts, circuit courts, clerks, members of the bar, constables, judges, justices of the peace, and others. The petitions concern the removal or relocation of courthouses, changing the time for holding courts, appointment of judges, stay laws, juries, clerks' fees, formation or changes in judicial circuits, judges' salaries, authority to celebrate the rites of matrimony, and exemptions from jury service.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: Joseph Allen, Clerk of the Court of Appeals, complains of the exposed & dangerous situation of the records & papers of the Court of Appeals (Richmond City - 1824/12/22); Clerks of the county courts asking for an increase in fees for their service (various counties - 1816), Inhabitants of Richmond asking for an amendment to the law so as to make the Mayor, Sergeant, Master of Police, & High Constable electable annually by the people, instead of by the Common Hall (1820/12/20); Judges of the Court of Admiralty asking for permission for the court to remain in its present location rather than move to Richmond when the capital is transferred from Williamsburg (Williamsburg City - 1779/10/16); Judgment of the Circuit Superior Court of Law & Chancery for Henrico & Richmond regarding the case of Charles Dimmock, Captain of the Public Guard, against the Commonwealth (Miscellaneous (Alphabetical) - Box 304, Folder 54); Chancery suit in the Superior Court of Chancery between John P. Shields & the Commonwealth for extra work done on Capitol Square (Miscellaneous (Alphabetical) - Box 304, Folder 58).
Division of County/New County - These are 1,974 records in the database from citizens of Virginia regarding the division of counties and the formation of new counties. These petitions also concern additions of parts of counties to other counties, changes to county boundaries, and protests against petitions asking for the division or formation of counties. The petitions often include maps and poll books. Noteworthy is a petition of the Committee of West Fincastle asking that they may be legally a part of the colony and for the creation of new counties (Fincastle Co. - 1776/10/08).
Divorce - There are 523 records in the database from citizens petitioning the General Assembly for a divorce from their husband or wife. These petitions often include court records, proceedings, depositions, and correspondence in support of the request.
Elections - These are 1,121 records in the database from citizens & voters regarding contested elections, separate election precincts, new election precincts, constitutional conventions, and the election of vestries. Noteworthy are the following petitions: Citizens of Fairfax County asking for a new election of delegates in the General Assembly because of a small pox outbreak at the polling place (1777/05/29); Freeholders & housekeepers of Winchester asking that the charter of the town be so amended as to secure an equal representation in the Common Council by dividing the town into four wards (1818/12/08), Trustees of Lexington asking for a law authorizing the qualified voters to elect annually an officer as mayor who shall be vested with all the power of a justice of the peace (Rockbridge Co. - 1850/01/25); and Tenants of the lands of William & Mary College asking for alterations or relief from their high rents & the right to vote (Williamsburg City - 1790/11/05).
Ferries/Packets - There are 624 records in the database from citizens, steamboat owners, steam packet companies, and bridge companies regarding the establishment of ferries or packets or the protest against such establishment. Additionally, there are petitions concerning the discontinuance of ferries, legislation, rates of ferriage, and compensation for financial injury as a result of the erection of bridges.
Noteworthy are the following petitions: Central Southern Rights Association asking for the charter of a company with the right to construct two steamers for the purpose of carrying passengers & freight from a point on the James River to Norfolk and across the Atlantic Ocean to Liverpool or other foreign ports (Norfolk Borough - 1851/12/13); M. F. Maury asking for a charter incorporating a company to establish a line of steamers from New York to ports of Brazil to be called the Amazonia Steamship Company (Norfolk Borough - 1852/01/28); Rumseian Society asking for an act granting James Rumsey exclusive privilege of making & lending his inventions including his steamboat (Berkeley Co. - 1788/11/15); James Rumsey asking for an act granting him the sole right of constructing, navigating, & employing boats constructed upon a newly invented model (Berkeley Co. - 1784/11/08); and George Augustine Washington, agent on behalf of President George Washington, asking for the discontinuance of the ferry across the Potomac River (Fairfax Co. - 1790/10/21).
Fishing/Oyster Industry - There are 235 records in the database from citizens, merchants, & owners of fisheries regarding oyster laws, dredging, the use of seines, weirs, & gill nets, slave & free black labor at fisheries, the use of dams & other obstacles preventing the passage of fish, the erection of slopes on dams to allow the passage of fish, and the protection of fisheries. Noteworthy is a petition from William Cleary asking for an amendment to the law so as to permit him to employ slaves & free negroes from Maryland & the District of Columbia at his fishery in Prince William County (Miscellaneous (Chronological) - 1841/01/07 & Prince William Co. - 1839/03/11).